We are back. I hope you are starting to
connect. Sorry about those technical
difficulties.
Um, and I know this wouldn't be the
first time we have technical
difficulties. So, put a one in the chat
if you're back with us. Uh, we're going
to do another prayer. Um, because maybe
you didn't even hear the first one. So,
um, if you're back, I hope you're all
back. I hope you click that new link.
So, if you're back with us, uh, put one
in the chat so that I know you're back
with us. Um, but I am going to pray
again because it's maybe you guys didn't
even hear my first prayer. So, I'm going
to go ahead and pray. Dear heavenly
father, thank you so much for all your
blessings and we're just thankful
because we do have this technology and
there's people who are joining this
broadcast from all kinds of places and
we ask you to be with us. We ask you to
bless this program and that we know that
there's an enemy that doesn't want it to
go out, but we ask you to bless it and
that everything we learn may be for um
for your glory and honor. Help us to
take better care of our bodies that are
the temple that you have given us. In
Jesus name we pray. Amen.
Yes, we have one. Great. Thank you so
much for joining us again and we
apologize for those technical
difficulties that you know happen. Uh
you're probably used to some to them
some of you maybe because they happen
they happen. Uh but I am so happy that
you have joined us and I wanted to tell
you when uh when this started happening
I was going to tell you that um this
title came to me because I was wondering
what to say you know I was actually
praying about what to you know what what
would be the next topic uh and that day
when I was actually praying about it I
happened to hear a podcast with this
very title Um, okay. Perfect title.
Thank you. Thank you guys for that
answer because um that was a very
captivating title to me. Is sugar a
poison? Uh, and but you know, you're
probably thinking, of course, sugar's a
poison. But I'm not going to give you
the answer because maybe the answer is
depends.
Maybe there's some nuances to that.
We'll see. Okay, we'll find out. But
before we get started, as you probably
know already if you've joined us before,
this is not meant to be uh any kind of
treatment for any kind of
um any kind of health uh kind of
condition
or anything else like that. We want you
to just be educated. This is
educational.
So that's important. And number two, I
want you to know for those of us who are
church members of the 7th Adventist
Church that I always use the Bible first
of all as a rule and I go by Isaiah
8:20. I hope all of you know that by now
if you didn't before the to the law and
the testimony. So I try to always be in
complete harmony with the Bible and the
spirit of prophecy. Bible and the spirit
of prophecy. Uh and of course the
testimony of Jesus is the spirit of
prophecy. And when it comes to health,
I've already, you know, said this many,
many times. I really really um hope that
some of you are already reading some of
these books if you haven't before.
Councils on diet and food and ministry
of healing. I hope that my I see
sometimes that my even my uh image is
kind of slowing down. I hope that uh I
hope that I'm not like I out of
synchrony like the other time I I saw my
video was out of synchrony for a while
but I'm I hope that my image is coming
out okay. Anyway, also scientific
evidence because even the spirit of
prophecy has told us that science is
important and we need to be credible
especially when we're talking about uh
these things to people who are not uh
believers. We need to be credible
because they might not take the Bible
and spirit of prophecy uh as something
that uh is of importance to them. So we
need to be able to speak to them in a
way that they will respect.
uh ministry of healing is such a
blessing. Yes, thank you Michelle. Thank
you for for for sharing that with us.
But I just want you to see these two
very important quotes for me. Anyway, it
says, "An knowledge of science of all
kinds if is power and advanced science
should be taught in our schools as
preparation for the work that is to
precede the closing scenes of the
earth's history." In other words, right
now. And the bottom uh says a practical
knowledge of science of human life is
necessary in order to glorify God in our
bodies. So I really hope that you
appreciate that I show you some of the
uh scientific evidence when I present
that material. And look at this these
verses or well the first quote uh um
from uh selective messages says God
wants us to have common sense. He wants
us to reason from common sense. And look
at the Bible in Matthew 16:10. It says
to be wise, wise, wise as serpents. The
heart of the prudent acquires knowledge.
The wise seeks knowledge. Okay. I I show
this every time because I just think
it's very very important. All right,
let's go ahead and get started. So, is
sugar actually a poison? Is it really?
Well, okay. So, now do we get started
with the really interesting stuff
because
well, of course, sugar when we talk
about sugar, what are we talking about
when we talk about sugar? Because it
could mean so many things, right?
First of all, let's talk about what we
think mostly that sugar when we think of
sugar, we usually think of white sugar,
table sugar, the white stuff that is in
these processed foods,
foods that contain sugar, pancakes. Oh,
but also hidden sugar. We'll talk about
this in a little while. Okay.
Uh for like ketchup. What? Ketchup. Ah,
well, I'll show you. Yes, some bread
sometimes have sugar. Spaghetti.
Sometimes we're even talking about
processed white flour because it acts
like sugar.
But
you know what I have to tell you? I have
to have to tell you this. I have been to
I have been to many many countries.
many countries
and I've been to the Adventist churches
in many many countries and I have been
to churches
where SDA
you know experts uh whatever people who
teach health
are telling sometimes people that we
should not eat sugar or fruit that we
should not eat fruit
because it has sugar.
I don't know if you any of you have
heard this.
Sometimes people are told they shouldn't
eat fruit.
What about fruit?
What about the sugar in fruit? What do
you think? Now I'm presenting to you
right here.
I think this is useful to see the
difference between the sugar in fruit
and the sugar in industrially produced
uh I would say food like products
because sometimes I would say they're
not really food. They're these products
that call themselves fruit food uh food.
They're not food.
So, the sugar in industrial products
contain much more sugar and fat
than any vegetable and there's no
nutritional value. You see that, right?
By the way,
these products over here that you see on
your right hand side,
look at this. Oh, you've heard this
before. Thank you for that. I don't know
how you say your name. Pasi. Pinasi.
Nice name. Look at this on the right
side.
sugar and fat together.
That's something that characterizes
a lot of these
industrial products,
highly processed
products. The sugar and the fat are
together. Now, let's think of this
because what?
Now, look at the uh left side of your
screen. There's fruits. There's avocado.
Look at that avocado.
Now, avocado is not high in sugar, is
it? It's high in what?
It's not sweet. If you taste it just
like that by itself, it's not really
sweet. Now, by the way, I've been to
Brazil. Brazil is a wonderful country,
by the way. They have awesome food.
But in Brazil, they don't put their
avocado on the salad usually or on their
tacos or whatever. They they make they
blend it. They use it for smoothies.
They use it as a fruit, you guys. But it
has a neutral flavor. It's not really
sweet if you think about it.
But it's high in what nutrient?
You haven't told me yet. I'll just tell
you then. It's high in fat as you know.
But what I want you to notice here
in nature, you usually don't fight sugar
and fat together. You don't find sugar
and fat together.
Fruits are usually high in fats like
avocados, nuts, seeds,
or high in sugar like most fruits.
Healthy fats are absolutely healthy. You
know why it's healthy? Number one,
because it's not saturated, highly
saturated. Number two, because it has
the fiber in it. All the fats that God
has made for our consumption already
have the fiber in it.
All the fats that God has made for our
consumption
have fiber.
Why? Because when the fiber is mixed
with the fat,
that fiber actually hangs onto the fat.
We don't absorb all of the fat. That
fiber hangs onto the fat. Also, the
glucose, by the way, cholesterol.
And the fiber, as you know, I hope you
know, is actually not digested.
Did you know that fiber is not digested?
Therefore, it goes through your intest,
stomach, small intestine, large
intestine, colon, whatever, bloom boom,
out your body. And it takes with it some
of that stuff, too. That's why it helps
to lower cholesterol because it the
cholesterol hangs onto the fiber, out
the body. Not all of it, but a lot. You
see, that's why it's important to always
eat the sugar with the fiber, the fat
with the fiber.
Does that make sense? I hope it does.
Anyway, what the point I'm trying to
make, industrial products have the sugar
and the fat together.
The fiber in or I'm sorry, the fat and
the sugar in the fruit are not together,
are separate.
Very important distinction.
Anyway, I've gone to these kind Yes,
that's good to know. Thank you, Cassie.
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Anyway,
I've gone to churches. My friends, I've
gone to churches
where people are being taught they
should not eat fruit
sometimes for some period of time,
but sometimes it's a long period of
time. So, I just want to show you, okay,
just to be clear on this, I just want to
leave this to you. You make your own
judgments. But I want to present these
to uh if our producer can move my Well,
I guess I can read it from my own um my
own uh my own slide. Okay,
look at Okay, thank you. Thank you to
our producer. Look at uh the first quote
there. It says the use of sugar. Well,
this we're going to talk about sugar
first. Okay. So what does um the
inspired pen of the uh spirit of
prophecy tell us about sugar? Look at
this. The free use of sugar in any form
tends to clog the system and is not
unfrequently the cause of disease.
Far too much sugar
is ordinarily used in food. Cakes, sweet
puddings, pastries, jellies, jams. Oh my
goodness, even back then
were used a lot. And these are active
causes of indigestion, especially
harmful of the custards with puddings in
which milk, eggs, and sugar. Oh my. Eggs
have fat, milk has fat. Put them with
sugar.
And there are the chief ingredients.
The use of milk and sugar taken together
should be avoided. Whoa. All right. Now,
let's look at these quotes.
[Music]
Now, it's talking about fruit. Oh, look
at those beautiful pictures. Don't they
look yummy? By the way, look at the
colors.
Do they look attractive to you? As
humans, we can see in all colors.
Carnivore animals. I'm saying the word
carnivore because a lot of people are
eating that kind of diet nowadays.
Carnivore animals like lions and cats do
not see all the colors. We as humans do.
We are designed to eat these fruits.
The Lord desires to The Lord desires
those living in countries where fresh
fruit can be obtained during a large
part of the year to awake the blessings
that have they have in this fruit. The
more we depend upon the fresh fruit just
just
look at that just as it is plucked from
the tree. In other words, in its most uh
fresh, in its most natural state, the
greater will be the blessing.
The bottom quote says, "It will be well
for us to do less cooking." Ah, it's not
great. Less work, less cooking, more raw
foods. Not all raw, but less cooking.
Less cooking. And to eat more fruit. And
it's what now? And it's what?
in its natural
state. Ah see in its natural state not
processed. Let us teach the people to
eat what now?
Freely
freely. Not constrained
not you know uh oh yeah only eat one one
grape today and two grapes tomorrow. No
no no no no. freely
of the fresh grapes, apples, peaches,
pears, berries, and all other kinds of
fruits that can be obtained.
So, I hope that's kind of clear. I hope
that is kind of clear. But let's go back
then to
why. So, I want to show you because I
there's so much confusion, guys. There's
so much confusion. This study here talks
about fructose.
Some Okay. Does that include dried
fruit? Oh, great question, Harriet.
Thank you, Harriet. Thank you for that
because that's a excellent question. All
right.
What about dried fruit? Is Okay. So,
see, is that in its most natural state
just as plot from the tree? Let's go
back to that.
You see how it says right here uh where
was it? Okay, the b the top the more we
depend upon the fruit just as it is
plucked from the tree. That means with
all its water content
once you dry it up the fruit shrinks.
So then it decreases in volume.
So you can definitely eat more of it
without realizing. I don't know if that
makes sense to you. The sugar is more
concentrated. Absolutely, Harriet. Yes,
the sugar is more concentrated. You tend
to eat more of it without necessarily
realizing it. Uh and also, you know, the
bottom um the bottom quote says, "It
would be well for us to do less cooking
and eat more fruit in its natural
state." And dried up is not necessarily
its most natural state. Now I will say
having said that I will say to you that
if you're going to sweeten something
dates are probably your best choice and
it is a dried fruit. Dates are really
nutritious.
So if you're going to use dried fruit,
use it moderately because it is higher
in concentration of sugar than regular
fruit. uh but it would be your second
choice. Your first choice is the fresh
fruit. That's my opinion. So, but it's a
awesome question. So, thank you. Thank
you for asking that. Now, when people
talk against fruit, they usually mean
fructose.
Oh, fructose is not used like glucose.
It's true. Fructose is not used like
glucose for energy. It goes straight to
your liver. It becomes fat. Yes. But
look at what this
study says. Industrial. Are you looking
at the title? Please look at the title.
Industrial.
You're welcome, Harriet. Industrial. Not
fruit. Are you looking at I hope you're
looking at the title because it's
couldn't be any clearer.
industrial not fruit fructose
intake is associated with the severity
of liver fibrosis liver damage.
So what kind of fructose again the
bananas the mangoes
the plums the apples the grapes?
Absolutely not.
What's industrial fructose, you guys?
What is industrial fructose?
We're talking about if you have any soda
in your house. I hope you don't, but if
you do, you can go and look at it. Look
at the ingredients. You most likely will
find industrial fructose, otherwise
known as high fructose corn syrup.
That's industrial fructose. So, um I put
right here down at the bottom a part of
part of the of the um text in this study
that kind of tells you more or less what
I the point that I wanted to bring out.
And it says the deletterious effect of
fructose was limited to industrial
fructose with no evidence for negative
effect of what?
Fruit. fructose.
No evidence for negative effect of fruit
fructose. Next time anyone tells you,
"Oh, we can't eat too much fruit because
show them this."
The apparent inconsistency might be
explained by the positive effects of
other nutrients. Like what? Like what?
What's in parenthesis right there? fiber
and antioxidants in fresh fruit.
In industrial food, in industrial food,
the glucose present in the high fructose
corn syrup
might even accelerate fructose
absorption, making industrial sugars
much more unhealthy.
Whoa!
My goodness gracious. Couldn't be any
more clearer. Does the sugar turn into
alcohol? Yes, sugar does turn into
alcohol. That is true. Yes, that is
true. That's how alcohol is actually
made. Whoa. Crazy. This is insane. Okay.
I hope you guys are taking pictures.
Well, I'll send you the the PDF so you
can have it. Okay. All right.
Now, look at this. Sugar, uric acid, and
the ideology. Ideology is the cause of
beginning. How how diseases start. Okay.
How be how a disease starts. Ideology of
diabetes and obes.
What's the number one thing over there?
What's how does it start the title? What
does it say?
Sugar.
And I'm putting right there. I'm
highlighting what I really want you to
get out of this out of this study
particularly. I mean, we can be talking
about all of these studies forever, but
I just wanted one take out, a point,
something to take home with from these
studies. And it's this. We found, for
example, that whereas fructose
from what?
Fructose from added sugars is associated
with hypertension. In this case, this is
an example.
Fructose from natural fruits is not. You
see that? Another example. Another
example. Fructose from added sugars is
associated with hyp hypertension and
fructose from natural fruits is not.
I want to show you something else you
guys. Because when we're talking about
fruit,
somebody asked, okay, what about dry
fruit? So, there's ways to actually
change natural fruit, right? So, there's
actually ways to process fruits in in
your house. So, what if you make
apple juice
in your house? That's still natural,
isn't it? Or what if you blend it? What
if you make smoothies with it? Well, I
just want to show you something so you
know.
We We need to just be aware of this. In
this study that I'm going to show you,
they actually did compare those three
things. I know this is kind of hard to
look at. I'm sorry, but it I just need
to
show it to you so that you are aware.
Sorry about the graphic, but the graphic
is the only thing that will explain this
point. There's the apple. The top line
in the graphic is the whole apple.
If you eat a whole apple,
what this graph is showing is that your
sugar as you see in the uh the line or
you know the the words on the left of
this graph are basically showing the
glucose going up. So what this graph is
showing first is that the glucose goes
up after you consume the apple. That's
what that's why the graph is going up
first. Is the sugar in your blood going
up. All right?
And then it comes down as it should as
it should. And what you see at the
bottom is minutes. That's the time that
passes after you eat the apple.
So it your sugar naturally goes up and
then it comes down as it should and it
notice how it comes down to the same
level as it was before more or less as
it should. Now the second line down
right under apple
is basically
apple smoothie if you will. It's blended
apple.
Okay. It's like apple sauce. It says
puree. You I don't know if you could see
the actual letters, but it says puree.
Apple sauce. Doesn't have added sugar.
It's just pureed apple. Applesauce. I
want you to notice the difference. Now,
the sugar does go up also as it should
when you eat the pureed apple. But when
it comes down,
notice the difference.
When it comes down, the applesauce makes
the sugar come down lower.
Do you see that?
The blended apple makes the sugar come
down lower than regular apple.
The bottom line of the three lines, the
the the one that's lower, the lowest
is juice.
What's the difference between puree and
juice?
Apple juice has zero fiber. Okay. The
puree, you don't take out the fiber.
It's like a smoothie. It's like a
blended applesauce, whatever. It still
has some fiber, but the fiber has been
disrupted.
Okay, that's the difference between
regular apple like you chew with your
own teeth. Your teeth are not like a
blender. You will never blend with your
teeth. Now, your stomach will do some of
the work, but that's your stomach, not
your teeth,
but
the uh blender will blend it much more
efficiently. Now
the difference, but what I want to say
is also that once you blend it, you
disrupt the fibers.
The bottom line is the juice. The
difference between the juice and the the
blended apple is that the juice has zero
fiber. Okay? You put it through an
extractor. You extract the fiber. And
look at how much lower. Do you see that
bottom line? the the sugar your blood
sugar this we're talking about blood
sugar it goes all the way down much
lower than what it was at the beginning
we are causing hypoglycemia
do you all know what that is
hypoglycemia
your blood sugar is going way down
because that sugar so what's happening
here why is your sugar going down so low
the lack of fiber I or the disruption in
the case of the applesauce by itself
without anything else. Okay, we're
eating the pure applesauce without
anything. Usually that doesn't happen.
You usually eat the applesauce with
something else.
But if you're drinking the apple juice
by itself, especially,
there's nothing to stop that sugar from
going right in.
No fiber, no nothing. It goes right in.
It gets absorbed directly into your
bloodstream.
that causes
uh an insulin response very fast
and the insulin makes the blood sugar go
down very fast, very low and you're
causing hypoglycemia
and therefore now so what's happening is
that your your body is responding with a
lot of insulin, a lot of insulin and
that's not normal. You don't want that
all day long. You're going to be having
too much insulin all day long. that can
be pro-inflammatory and can lead to um
in metabolic diseases and weight gain
and all kinds of issues.
We don't want to disrupt or eliminate
the fiber from our foods. Therefore,
yes, fruit is good, but in its most
natural state,
the less we disrupt it, the better.
There's one ex exception to this rule.
The blending does not seem to um
alter so much in the case of berries
because they've done studies with
blended berries and they don't actually
have that effect. In fact, uh, with this
particular study, they actually fed
people slices of wheat bread or rye
bread, and they measure how much their
glucose went up just with the bread. And
then they actually fed them the bread
plus blended berries. And the blended
berries instead of making the sugar go
up higher, they actually prevented the
sugar from going as high as what it had
gone up with the bread. So the sugar
went up lower
with the bread and the berries that with
the bread alone.
So the berries actually made the sugar
go up lower, which is very interesting.
So berries are the exception at least
with that what of what all the fruits
that have been studied. I guess berries
have this sort of negative effects in in
the case of blood sugars going up. So
that's pretty good to know. Uh can that
cause diabetes? Ask Lewis
if you do it a lot. Yes. Like if you're
constantly uh drinking sugary
drinks
particularly uh sodas for instance and
that leads to weight gain. All of this
extra calories and extra sugar will
convert to fat and that will that might
anyway lead to uh insulin resistance uh
which can then lead to pre-diabetes
which can then lead to diabetes. Yes, it
can eventually become diabetes possibly.
That is possible. Okay. I also wanted to
show you um another thing with the
berries.
Uh this one is also with berries where
they showed um something very similar
because in this case they didn't even
feed people um bread. They actually gave
them sugar water you guys. And with the
sugar water, they found something
similar than what they did with the with
the bread. And so what you see up here,
I'm sorry for these these graphs. They
look so technical. They look graphy,
right? But what I just want to say the
following the the triangle you see and
it says reference where you see the
triangle. Wherever you see a triangle,
it means sugar water. Triangle means
sugar water.
So what you see here is that with the
sugar water, the blood glucose that's on
the the graph on the left, the blood
glucose went up and then really down.
Same as what we saw before with the
apple juice. But if you if you give
people sugar water and then you give
them blended berries, the the blood
sugar doesn't go up doesn't go down so
low. So it's what we saw just before
with the bread, right? So the sugar
doesn't go that you don't cause
hypoglycemia
when you give people the berries. What
you see on the right is very interesting
you guys because if you look at the uh
the label on the graph it says fatty
free fat free fatty acids. That's fat.
That's fat in the blood. If you give
people
sugar,
sugar
alone, the triangle, I don't know if you
can see this at the end towards the 80
minutes, the 120 minutes. Do you see
this all the way to the right? How the
triangle line goes up higher than the
other two? That's because there's more
fat in the blood of the people who are
drinking sugar water. Do you think that
can happen if you're drinking soda? Do
you think that can happen if you're
drinking juice? You bet it can.
Therefore, if you're drinking soda or
sugar drinks or whatever,
they could be they you could be
releasing fat into your blood. That's
what's happening in this case. But with
the berries, it's not happening.
Interesting.
Interesting. Interesting. Interesting.
Interesting. Okay. Anyway, so after
seeing all of this, I'm going to ask you
a question.
Be ready to answer, you guys. Okay, are
are you ready? My question to you is,
oh, sorry, the animation didn't work.
The answer came up. I should have put it
in a different slide. I forgot that this
isn't a PowerPoint presentation
necessarily. It's with the um it's with
the P with this different program. Okay,
never mind. So, uh is the sugar from
fruit a poison?
What do you think? Well, I put the
answer already. Never mind. I put this
answer as no because as you can see, the
sugar from fruit is different, isn't it?
I think I've showed you enough evidence.
I hope I have. Put a one in the chat if
you think I put enough evidence that the
sugar from fruit is completely different
from industrial sugar. Oh, by the way,
we're talking about fructose. So, let me
just reward that. Let me just re say
that again. Put a one in the chat if you
have been convinced. I hope so. That the
fructose from fruit is totally different
than the fructose from sodas or fructose
from any highly processed fruit. Thank
you. Yes. Thank you. Thank you. Thank
you. If you need to show this to
anybody, feel free to show it. I will
send you guys the PDFs. You can show
this video again and again because it's
totally different. The fruit that the
the sugar that God put in fruit is
healing to us.
Yes. Thank you, Louis. The Bible tells
us we can eat fruit. Yes. Absolutely
wrong. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you.
Okay. Thank you guys for putting all
those ones. Absolutely. Yes. Thank you.
Thank you. I think God has given us the
best food and he put he put
the medicine in our food. All right. But
the question now is, what about
refined sugar?
What about refined sugar?
Is that good for us? Bad for us? Is it
poison?
What do you think? Is refined sugar
good? Bad? Poison?
[Music]
Is poison like an exaggerated
a word? I don't know. All right. Well,
let me show you something very
interesting. Okay, let's start talking
about actually sugar. Sugar, okay, white
sugar. Could it either sucrose, which is
this, you know, like the stuff you put,
you know, when you're making a pie, or
high fructose corn syrup, which is more
like the industrialized fructose that
are in all the industrial stuff that you
buy, like most of the stuff you buy at
the supermarket, you guys, is fructose.
very very cheap sugar. That's why they
put it there because it's cheaper than
sucrose. That's why they use it. Bad bad
you guys. Not good. Very bad. No, no,
no. All right. Thank you. Okay. Let me
show you something. This study talks
about the liver
diets and non-alcoholic
fatty liver disease.
Whoa. This is a this is this is becoming
quite the epidemic nowadays you guys. I
used to work at a clinic. I was seeing
this is 15 years ago. It's not even now.
I don't even work there anymore. 15
years ago I was seeing children
children
with their liver enzymes
going up already
with uh beginning stages of fatty liver.
Bad, bad, bad, bad. All right, let me
show you uh this um illustration from
this very uh study. It talks about the
three ways in which you can get fatty
liver disease. All right, there's the
basically three ways and I want you to
notice the three red arrows
that go into the liver.
Um, and so, okay, let's look at the one
in the right. There's all these like
yellow uh blobs that you see over here,
and it says fatty acid released from
adabos tissue. What does it mean? It
means that if we carry excess body fat
in our own bodies, if we have excess
weight, in other words, that excess
weight, that extra adipose tissue
basically releases
fatty acids, fat that goes into our
liver. So just being overweight in
itself in and of itself is a a risk
factor. All right? So having extra
weight.
The one over here in the middle says
fatty acids from diet. All right. Fatty
acids from diet.
In other words, when we eat a lot a
highfat diet, highfat
diet,
don't let anyone tell you that a highfat
diet is good for you because that's the
new thing everybody's talking about. Oh
yeah, carbs are bad. Fat is good. Wait a
minute. We just saw that fruit is
actually good and it's a carb. Fructose
is a carb. But where does it come from?
Oh, I'm gonna talk about honey. Thank
you. I am going to talk about honey. I
will tell you about that at the end
towards the end. Okay. All right. But
let's go back to fat.
It's very clear here that high fat,
eating high fat, the fat goes straight
to your liver
if it's in excess, of course, and if
it's bad fat, because we already talked
about the good fat. The good fat has
fiber.
Okay. But I want you to look at this the
weird strange uh term over here on the
left. What in the world does that is
that
denovo lipogenesis? What is that? Denovo
lipogenesis.
Very weird term. I'll just tell you what
it is. It's when the liver transform
other things that are not fat into fat.
So other things that are not fat,
mainly sugar. It could be protein, but
it's very hard to have excess protein.
But it's very easy to eat excess sugar.
So all that excess sugar, especially if
it's fructose, because the excess
glucose gets used up for energy. But you
could eat you could have extra extra
glucose if you're eating a lot of
calories. Definitely you can have extra
glucose. But if you're eating a lot of
fructose that is industrialized, that
has no fiber, all of that is going
straight to the liver. Straight to the
liver. And guess what? It is converted
into
there's no way to store it.
Is going to get converted into
what?
F A T
F A
Now
later on this very study that I'm
showing you this illustration I show you
the title it says right here I
highlighted it for you increased intake
of carbohydrate
not in the form of fruit
it says sweetened beverages
increases the risk of what?
Number one, obesity. Number two, type
two diabetes. Metabolic syndrome is when
you have high high cholesterol, high you
know weight and uh in glucose in the
body and glucose in the blood and
hypertension. All of it together. That's
metabolic syndrome. Fatty liver,
cardiovascular disease, all of these
things are connected. Like we talked
about the first time we were together my
first presentation we talked about how
all of this is to comes together they're
connected.
Okay. Later on it talks about sucrose
sweetened beverages. You see that
sucrose sweetened beverages increase
increases visceral atapose tissue.
That's the very dangerous fat that's
inside that kind. You don't see it
because it's not subcutaneous.
Subcutaneous fat. You can actually touch
it, right? You can actually grab it.
That's not the most dangerous kind of
fat you guys. It's the one around your
organs. That's the visceral adapose
tissue as well as liver fat
accumulation.
That's the that is what sweetened
beverages is doing to you. Over here
down at the bottom it says high
consumption of fructose
from what? From mangoes,
from grapes,
from kiwis. No, no, no, no, no, no, no,
no, no, no. From
in the form of it says right here, high
fructose corn syrup. Where are you going
to find that?
Just about every single product in the
supermarket.
Results in increased oxidative stress
and insulin resistance. What's oxidative
stress? We talked about it when we
talked about cancer. I think you have to
go back and look at it. is damage at the
cellular level. Go look at it.
Which are risk factors for what's NF? N
AFD N Ald
non-alcoholic fatty liver disease and
type 2 diabetes. Oh my goodness.
I hope it's clear. I hope it's clear. I
hope. Anyway, conclusion,
sugar affects our bones. You bet it
does. Yes, it does. Thank you, Rihanna.
Rihanna.
Okay, you guys.
So, some diets have been linked to the
development of non-alcoholic
fatty liver disease, notably
notably in animal models.
High fat.
I I I couldn't show you anything more
clear than this. Highfat and ketogenic
diets.
Don't let anyone tell you that a
highfat, low carb diet is good for you.
It's right here.
A highfat diet will give you fatty
liver. A keto diet will give you fatty
liver. It's right here. Show them this.
It's right there.
Nevertheless, down at the bottom. Okay.
Nevertheless, based on current evidence,
we
who the experts on liver disease. That's
we. Okay. That's who. We would recommend
a diet. How? What does it say? Low in
fat.
Notably in what kind of fat?
What?
saturated
fatty acids. Where are saturated fatty
acids found?
Where are saturated fatty acids found?
Number one, all animal products, unless
you take out the fat. So, okay, egg
whites, fine, don't have the saturated
fat. Or skin milk, fine, doesn't have
the fat. Everything else has the fat and
it's saturated mostly. Number one source
of saturated fat in the diet. Do you
know it's not red meat?
It's cheese.
And actually, there's a higher source of
saturated fat that is not even animal.
It's coconut oil. Sorry to tell you
that, but it's highly saturated. It has
twice the percentage of saturated fat
than lard. You can use it on your skin
or eat the coconut with the fiber.
notably in saturated fat and low
in refined carbohydrates.
You don't have to eat low fruit, low in
refined carbohydrate, notably by
reducing what? What exactly? What are we
talking about? soft drink consumption in
patients with non-alcoholic
fatty liver disease, which just about
everybody nowadays has at least the
beginnings of, as these nutritional
factors may play a pivotal role in
non-alcoholic fatty liver disease.
Butter. Yes, thank you. Butter. Butter.
Very saturated fat. Absolutely. Okay.
Now when we talked about my first
presentation, 10 days to better health,
if you want to look at it, you can see
we talked about insulin resistance and
we saw that an insulin sensitive liver
is a healthy liver, but an insulin
resistant liver is a fatty liver.
Okay? Therefore, if you have insulin
resistance, that leads to fatty liver.
So, it's very much connected to insulin
resistance. It's all connected. So, go
back to that. Somebody asked about maple
syrup. That's a very good question
because it's I would say somewhat better
than refined sugar, but it does not have
the fiber. So, I would not eat it in
high amounts. I would use it in small
amounts. Um, it's a much more um I would
say natural product. Comes from a tree.
has some trace, you know, uh, nutrients.
So, I would use it, but in small
amounts.
Better than maple syrup. That's why I
was saying probably the better one,
better choice is dates because it
actually has the fiber. So, you can make
date paste, uh, chop the dates. There's
actually date sugar out there, but
that's a little bit more it's a little
bit more processed. So, I would I would
say buy the dates and make the date
paste yourself.
I think that's a better choice. That's
my own personal opinion on that. All
right, let's move on. I want to show you
another important point here. It talks
about excessive intake of sugar.
Obviously, it's talking about processed
sugar here as well.
But now it's not talking about fatty
liver disease. It's actually talking
about inflammation, which is a bigger
word. is actually more comprehensive if
you will. It uh encompasses more things
because down here uh highlighted in this
uh soft orange uh light orange color it
says obesity, cardiovascular disease,
metabolic syndrome, type 2 diabetes.
It's kind of like the same stuff we were
talking about before. So it kind of goes
to show that they're all connected
again. Um, and down here says consuming
high levels of dietary hexos. That's
just another word for sugar. Don't worry
about that term. It's just sugar. But
now it's talking about other kinds of
diseases though. Look at this. It's
talking about rheumatoid arthritis,
multiple sclerosis,
psoriasis, inflammatory bowel disease.
Now we're talking about like Crohn's
disease and lowgrade chronic
inflammation.
Now we're talking about diseases that
are more in you know the realm of
autoimmune diseases
where sugar can be also possibly
connected
because
of this inflammatory
uh aspect of it inflammation.
Wow.
Do fatty liver give symptoms? Maybe when
it's advanced you can start maybe having
uh some jaundice maybe but definitely it
will appear first in the blood and might
not have any symptoms. So if you're uh
uh liver enzymes come out um
that are not uh not normal abnormal. So
I would definitely be checking you know
and if your if your doctor is doing a
comprehensive you know uh blood check uh
blood examination they probably will
find it before you have any symptoms
honestly I think. All right look at
this. Yikes. Understanding the link
between sugar and cancer.
Now people always say sugar feed can
feeds cancer. Well, it's not directly.
It's not like directly feeding the
cancer. It does kind of feed you but
indirectly feeding the cancer. But there
is a link. Okay. So there's a link
between sugar and cancer because it says
right here that high sucrose that's
white table sugar basically and high
fructose diets activates several
mechanisms
including inflammation. You see so it's
like the the the sugar leads to
inflammation.
um glucose and lipid metabolic pathways
suggesting a causal link between excess
sugar consumption and cancer development
and progression that is independent of
weight gain. So there is a link there is
a link between sugar and cancer. Uh so
see how sugar is linked between uh
there's a link between cancer and all
these other
diseases.
Okay.
But
I think there's one thing that's even in
my view even worse. I don't know. It
could be just as bad. I would think
maybe it's just as bad in in my view
it's worse. But I don't know what you
think. maybe you'll think is just as
bad, but it depends on the person, I
guess.
Look at all these
foods. Some of them are sweet,
like we have, of course, the sweetened
drinks, cake,
ice cream,
but some of them are savory like pizza,
burgers, whatever. Right?
So,
what's what's in common with all of
these uh foods?
They're all highly processed, right?
They're all highly or actually we would
call them all maybe junk food, right?
Interestingly though, all of these
probably have sugar
even though they're savory. And I want
to show you something kind of worrying,
scary almost, and it's this.
It says study
sugar. And look at that word right after
sugar.
That is sugar that is hidden. You see
the the picture that they put here with
the with this article. It's not even
sweet things. It's all savory stuff.
But it says sugar.
Sugar hidden where
in junk food, you guys.
Junk. Yeah, they're tasty. They're
tasty. They make it tasty because these
they put the sugar with salt and the fat
usually don't they don't go together.
Sugar hidden in junk food is what?
Are you looking at the title? I hope
you're reading the title with me.
It might sound exaggerated, hyperbolic.
Maybe
I didn't say it.
Sugar hidden in junk food. Sugars and
everything. Yes. Is eight times more
addictive than cocaine.
Sounds exaggerated, doesn't it?
Hyperbolic. Maybe they're just putting
that to kind of clickbait. Clickbait.
Well,
here's a study, you guys.
Here's a study. You can just go and look
for it. read it yourself.
I'll show you what they did. By the way,
I'm going to just kind of show you the
picture of the researchers who did the
study.
You know what they did? By the way,
here's a rat in front. Here's some Oreo
cookies. Did you know Oreo cookies are
vegan?
Oreo cookies are vegan.
Does the word vegan automatically
translate to healthy?
Yes or no?
Because a lot of people, a lot of people
tell me, "Oh, such and such is vegan,
but look at how unhealthy they are."
Well, that's because vegan is not
necessarily
healthy.
There's a lot of healthy or vegan things
that are super unhealthy, like Oreo
cookies.
So, this is what these people did, okay?
They took a bunch of rats
and they made them. This I mean, it
sounds terrible, actually. I think it's
terrible how some of these animals are
treated. It's true. They made them
addicted to cocaine.
They made them addicted to cocaine. They
were addicted.
Once they were addicted, they put them
in an enclosure, I guess, a cage or
something. And there were two levers,
one for the cocaine, which they were
already addicted to. And they knew how
to press the lever, it would release the
cocaine. They were already trained to do
that. On the other side, there was a
lever that would release sugar.
And so they were free to roam
and go to each lever. Once they figure
out the other lever had sweetened some
kind of sweetened liquid or substance,
they went to the sugar. Even though they
were addicted to the cocaine, they went
over there. They went to the sugar.
That's what happened.
So, as you probably know,
yeah, it is horrible. As you probably
know, we have a dopamine pathway in your
brain. You probably already heard about
dopamine being this neurotransmitter
that is associated with just about every
single addiction.
It is the neurotransmitter that help us
helps us to feel pleasure. And you see
that these neurons, you see these uh
arrows
that extend, the neurons are actually
pretty long. They actually extend the
neurons themselves to different parts of
our brain, including this front part
called the frontal lobe and the uh parts
of our brain that have to do with
cognition.
And so these parts of the brain
have to do with cognitive control,
with motivation,
with inhibition.
These parts of the brain get damaged
with addictions
and sugar stimulates them
just as much as any other
addictive substance. That's what they
have found. I'm going to start um
jumping around because I'm running out
of time. But I just wanted to show you
this comparison you guys. Here on the
left you see a normal brain and what you
see in the red are what are called
dopamine receptors.
When a person starts to take in an
addictive substance they produce
excessive dopamine
and this excessive dopamine starts to
damage the brain. Therefore, the brain
has to put on the brakes and has to
lower the excessive dopamine. And what
it does is that it reduces the amount of
dopamine receptors to put on the brakes.
Basically, it's too much stimulation and
that is too much damage basically long
term. So the the what happens is that
there is a um there is a reduction of
these dopamine receptors. So what we see
here in the middle is the brain of a
person who's been using cocaine for one
month. And what you notice here is that
there is a reduction of the orange
color.
That means this person has less dopamine
receptors. meaning
they no longer feel pleasure with normal
things. If they eat an apple, it's not
pleasurable.
If they hug a loved one, they don't feel
pleasure. They only feel pleasure with
cocaine. Now,
after four months,
same thing. They haven't recovered.
And I want to show you that the same
thing could happen
with sugar.
In fact, they have found parallels
with addiction and obesity.
Addiction to drugs and obesity seem to
have the same patterns.
Is it possible that some people who are
obese have a hard time losing weight
because there as there's an actual
substance addiction?
Is it possible?
Here's another comparison.
There's a normal brain up up in the uh
uh left corner top
and you see the different brains.
There's a brain of an addicted person
that's addicted to cocaine. The bottom
right is an addict an alcoholic
and the top right is an obese
individual.
Do you see how they all have a um
lessening? There's less
uh of these dopamine receptors. What is
happening?
What is happening? There's maybe an
addictive process going on here. And in
fact, these people who are producing
these foods know very well what they're
doing.
You can look this up. Look up the term
Bliss Point.
All of these companies know what it is
and they know it very well. And they
hire people called food scientists.
They call they they're called food
scientists. They study this
and that's what they do. They make the
products to be as attractive as
possible. Perfect amounts of sugar,
salt, and fat. So when you eat that one,
you know, you open that bag of cookies,
you eat one or you can't just eat one.
You can't eat one potato chip.
You cannot eat just one
Cheeto or whatever.
You can't.
You have to eat half the bag.
The concent the combination of fat and
sugar appears to be especially
powerful
for the brain.
Yes. The bliss point refers to optimal
combination of salt, sugar, and fat that
triggers pleasurable taste sensation
makes food irresistibly cravable.
Absolutely. Thank you for giving us the
precise definition of bliss point. All
food manufacturer producers know exactly
what it is. They use it.
And all of these foods, people who have
been addicted
to both drugs and food,
I've heard I've read an author who said
who was actually addicted to drugs and
then food once she overcame the drug
addiction became addicted to food. And
she says it's way more difficult to
overcome food addiction than drug
addiction. You know why? Because once
you leave the drugs, they're gone from
your life.
But what about the food? Everywhere you
go, it's socially acceptable to consume
it. And people push you. What? You're
not going to have another You're not
going to have a piece of cake. Come on.
I made this pie. You got to taste it.
What do you mean you're not going to
have another one?
Even at the church,
when I go to the church,
all kinds of churches where I go to,
they have this beautiful buffet. Please,
no one get offended. I always tell
people the churches where I go, please
don't be offended. You have a wonderful
healthy sometimes
wonderful healthy food over here and
over here you have the table. And when I
say the table, they always know which
table I'm talking about. The table, the
other table.
And it's the equivalent of heroin for
some of us, myself included.
I am a food addict, a sugar addict.
It's hard. Some of you might relate. I
don't know. But it's hard. It's like an
alcoholic. You put the beer in front of
them.
It's not easy, you guys. It's a
struggle. Yes, it is a struggle. It's
not easy when they put the equivalent of
heron in front of you and push you to
eat it. What? You're not going to have
some?
It's hard.
Here are the uh most addictive foods.
They've done this study using the Yale
uh food addictive uh food addictiveness
scale or whatever. Yale came up with
that and other universities have done
studies of the most addictive foods.
Number one, pizza. Pizza has sugar.
You know where?
Where's the sugar in the pizza?
The sauce.
The sauce has sugar. And of course, the
white flour plus the cheese. That's a
whole different thing. The cheese is
addictive because of the casein. We
talked about casein when we talked about
uh cancer.
We talked about, you know, the cancer
thing, right? But we didn't even talk
about the fact that casein once you
ingest it becomes quesomorphine. Queso
morphine. What does that sound to you?
Anyway, you already know. Well, I don't
know if you know how much sugar is on
these uh terrible drinks.
Do you know that some of these drinks
have up to 17
17 teaspoons? Would you ever put 17
teaspoons in coffee?
Look at this. 15 teaspoons.
You don't even realize how much sugar
we're consuming because some of these
drinks of course have sodium. So they,
you know, you don't even realize how how
much sugar there's in these. Okay, I
want to end with this. This
can be reversed. This addiction can be
reversed. Praise God.
Addiction can be reversed, you guys.
With one of the eight principles of
health. Did you know? Did you know that
one of the eight principles of health is
the cure for addiction? I didn't know if
you knew, but here it is. It's up in the
top.
brain recovery. So addiction is a brain
disease. The brain is damaged is
physically damaged with addiction. The
person who's addicted no longer has the
ability to, you know, to stay awake
because the brain is damaged. This it's
no longer a thing of um of will. They
don't have the willpower.
But the brain can recover. There's
plasticity.
And it says right there, brain recovery
with prolonged
abstinence.
The brain can recover, but only if you
stay away from the addictive substance.
Only if you Oh, come on.
Once a week, it's okay to have a little
bit in moderation. It won't hurt. No,
no, no, no. When there's an addiction,
moderation kills.
When there's an addiction, moderation
does not work. Never. Never, ever, ever.
You cannot be moderate with an addictive
substance.
Therefore, you see on the left a healthy
brain. In the middle, you see the brain
with one month of abstinence. It's not
quite recovered yet.
But on the right, do you see what
happens after 14 months of abstinence?
You see that the orange is starting to
come back. The brain is starting to
heal.
Is starting to heal. Wow. Abstinence is
one of the It's the same as temperance,
right? or very close because temp real
temperance is eating the good things
moderately but staying completely away
abstaining from the bad things. That's
true temperance. All right. So to
conclude,
is sugar a poison?
H is sugar a poison? Well, it depends
what sugar you're talking about, right?
What sugar are we talking about? I'm not
going to answer this uh quote directly.
I'm going to read or I'm not going to
answer this question directly. I'm going
to eat read some quotes.
So, we read this, right?
Sugar clo clocks the system. It hinders
the working living machine. I frequently
sit down to the tables of brethren and
sisters and see that they have great
amount great amounts of milk and sugar.
These clog the systems and irritate the
digestive system and affect the what?
Affect the what?
Oh my affect the brain.
Anything that hinders the active motion
of the living machinery affects the
brain very directly.
How does she know?
And from the light given me, sugar when
largely used is more injurious than
meat.
My goodness gracious.
Sugar when largely used is more
injurious than meat.
My oh my. Yes. Because it's addictive.
It's a drug. And you know what she talks
when she what she says about meat? She
says to stay away completely.
By the way, if you look up some of the
things she says about sugar, you might
be confused. If you look up LG white
sugar, well, in some places she says,
"Well, I use a little bit." Oh, no. Stay
completely away. Oh, no. Well, you're
you're going to get confused. And this
is why. because she says let the diet
reform be progressive. In other words,
for some people the changes might have
to be step one step at a time. So at the
beginning she did some use some sugar
and then later on she stopped and she
made the changes progressively. All
right. Okay. Let's talk about honey.
I'm going to read some Bible verses to
you. Proverbs 14:13.
My son, eat honey because it is good.
The and the honeycomb which is sweet to
your taste.
All right, that's chapter 24. Chapter
25.
Have you found honey?
Eat only as much as you need,
lest you be filled it filled with it and
vomit. Huh?
only a little bit then and then later on
in the same chapter it is not good to
eat too much or much honey right it's
not good to eat much honey therefore eat
it moderately
eat it good but only moderately I use it
you guys so I am technically not vegan
because people who consume honey are
technically not vegan so I'm not
technically not vegan because I use
honey I buy it from somebody who lives
nearby my house who makes it. So, it's
local honey and I keep it only for when
somebody is sick in my house if they
have flu, cold, covid, any of those
things. And I actually uh use about two
tablespoons and I take the juice of
about four lemons and I put about a
quarter of a uh onion and about four or
five cloves of garlic. blend it all and
drink the, you know, well, not drink the
whole thing, two or three tablespoons at
a time every two hours. That seems to
kill it. It's an antibacterial and
antiviral because of the honey, the the
whatchamacallit, the garlic and the
onion. But the honey has medicinal
uh per medicinal capabilities because it
actually helps the throat. So anybody
who has cough or sore throat, the honey
itself
uh is very good for it. They in fact
they've done actual studies where they
have compared cough syrup and honey.
The two have the same effect.
So I do recommend it actually. All
right, I will finish with this verse.
1 Corinthians 6:19 and 20 says, "Or do
you not know that your body is the
temple of the Holy Spirit who is in you,
whom you have from God, and that you are
not your own? For you were bought at a
price. Therefore, glorify God in your
body and your spirit, which are God's."
You should only use honey that has been
tested. Okay. Thank you. Yeah. Uh and
also
from age one and above never to a baby.
Sugar is dangerous. Yes, sugar is
dangerous. You cannot metabolize you.
Sugar is very very dangerous. Um
machines have manuals and the Bible is
our manual, isn't it? Read yours. Thank
you. White and refined sugar is
dangerous very much. Sugar addiction is
e easy to kick with 12 weeks. Yeah. 12
weeks. In 12 weeks, like a 12st step. Is
that what we're talking about?
12 weeks. Yeah, I think so. Yeah. With
time you can do it.
Yes. Yes. Yes. Okay. So, let me finish
with uh giving you my
web page in case uh someone here doesn't
have it yet. Healthforday.net.
Healthfor.net.
I think some of you have already uh gone
because you've sent me some messages
through there. You can definitely
contact me through my web page and if
you haven't yet, you can download the
10day
challenge that I have right there is a
10 day of um menu plus recipes. The
10day Daniel challenge
to eat whole food plant-based. Maybe
I'll ask my uh producer to put me back
on the screen.
Maybe. There we go. All right. So, you
can download it. Okay. Download the
10day and try it because it is good for
you. If you haven't seen the 10 days to
better health um the first presentation
that I've done with um
with true uh health Tuesdays, I
recommend you watch it because it can
really change your health. It can
transform your life. I do it for my work
all the time. So, I know it works. So,
if there's no more question, I love the
health challenge. Thank you. Uh yeah,
re-watch it. Yes. Thank you. Thank you
for all your wonderful
I will send the PowerPoint. I have sent
all the PowerPoints. So, if you still
haven't gotten yours of the previous
messages, make sure you ask for the
PowerPoints. Okay. So, we're going to
end with prayer. Let's pray. Dear
heavenly father, thank you so much for
the opportunity to do these programs
true health Tuesdays and thank you for
the wisdom that you have given us, for
the information, the ability to know all
this wonderful information about our
bodies, how to better care for them. The
food that you have given us that is so
wonderful. medicinal that has so many
nutrients that help our bodies and thank
you Lord for giving us the light through
our health message. Help us to not only
keep it to ourselves and improve our own
health but help us to be tools, help us
to be um help us to be ambassadors of
your word and your health message. help
us to take it to others who need it as
well, who who might be suffering, who
might benefit from this wonderful
information and that maybe in through
these messages might even get to know
you, our healer, our God, our savior.
Thank you once again. Be with us the
rest of this week until the Sabbath day
when we meet again. In Jesus name we
pray. Amen. And amen. Thank you again
for being with us and we'll see you in
two more weeks. I think we're going to
start a series of di about diabetes. I
have a lot of uh information about
diabetes. In fact, our producer Gigi,
she is the one who suggested that we do
diabetes and I said, "I have four
programs." She's like, "Yes, let's do
diabetes." So, it's going to take us
about a couple months to go through all
of them. So, tell your friends. We're
going to do a series on diabetes. We're
going to give first of all a um
introduction that we're probably going
to talk a little bit more about you know
the underlying um condition that takes
that causes diabetes and then we're
going to talk about the best diet for
diabetes. Then we're going to talk about
the best exercise for diabetics and not
just diabetics as you probably know
because uh it's insulin resistance which
is connected with all these metabolic
diseases like hypertension, high
cholesterol and obesity and fatty liver.
So anyone who is interested in any of
those conditions should join and then
we're going to talk about other
lifestyle things you can do to prevent
all of those things. So not just
exercise and diet. And then at the end,
we're going to conclude on how to make
these changes because it's not easy as
you probably know. How to, you know,
incorporate new habits, how to have more
self-control, that's hard, all of those
things. So, it's probably going to take
us about four or five maybe uh programs
to do all of this. So, invite your
friends and thank you once again and God
bless you. We'll see you in two weeks.
Bye everybody. Thank you.
And God bless you.